<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[A short treatise of the sacraments generally, and in speciall of baptisme, and of the Supper] [written by Iohn Prime ...]</title>
            <author>Prime, John, 1550-1596.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1582</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10114</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20372</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1280</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22102314</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22102314</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25051</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10114)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25051)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1734:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[A short treatise of the sacraments generally, and in speciall of baptisme, and of the Supper] [written by Iohn Prime ...]</title>
                  <author>Prime, John, 1550-1596.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[95] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Christopher Barker, printer to the Queenes Most Excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1582]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁸.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: t.p. lacking; beginning-signature A₄ of defective Sion College Library copy spliced at end; tightly bound and cropped.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sacraments --  Church of England.</term>
               <term>Baptism --  Church of England.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Church of England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:25051:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25051:51"/>
            <head>To the right honourable Sir Francis Walſingham Knight, chiefe Secretarie to her Maieſtie, Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celler of the Order, &amp; one of her high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes priuie Counſell, all grace and peace in Chriſt Ieſu.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He endeleſſe making of bookes was a vanitye in the dayes of Salomon, when Printing was not. The end of all, is the ſeate of God. Certainely men may not make it a light matter in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to trouble the worlde with vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table writinges. Yet, as in the ſhewebread that was ſhewed to the people as a figure of Chriſt the olde loaues hauing ſerued to their uſe were remoued, and other ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in their roome, yet ſtill breade in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, &amp; twelue loaues in nomber: ſo thoſe writinges that figure out Chriſt, and ſet foorth Chriſtian duetye, may be often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times treated of, and eftſoones repeated and added to other mens doinges, not withſtanding no great variety in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or maner of handling. It hath beene thought expedient I write &amp; publiſhe this litle treatiſe. Wherupon (right Honorable)
<pb facs="tcp:25051:2"/>therewithal I haue thought it my bounde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> duetie humbly to preſent it to your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours viewe: the rather, in parte to excuſe mine ouer great boldneſſe elſe when, but principally, to craue ſuch furtheraunce in the ſetting out therof, as your honors piety and place accuſtometh to ſhewe, to ſuch as in their calling with their talentes, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fiue, two, or but one, labour to ſet foorth the trueth, to inſtruct the ſimple, &amp; to ſaue ſoules. This hath bene mine en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuor: the ſucceſſe whereof is to be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for of the almightie and merciful God, who alwayes preſerue your honour to the glorie of his name, the benefite of his Church and this our countrie, in all faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeruice to her Maieſtie, and great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte of her louing ſubiectes in the Lorde. Februarie. 14. Anno. 1582.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and bounden Iohn Prime.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:25051:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the vſe of all things is moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, ſo is their abuſe moſt perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious. Many excellent thinges are ſpoken of the Sacraments of Chriſtian faith: They are the Lordes owne ordinances, memorials of diuine promiſes, monuments of our duety, ſignes to the word which we profeſſe, aſſured ſeales of his good will, ſtrong bandes whereby we ſtande bounde first to God in obedience, and then in mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al loue amongſt our ſelues. Notwithſtanding, theſe ſacred myſteries, the very inſtrumentes of the holy Ghoſt, haue they not bene of olde, or are they not now either vnthankefully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, or vnworthily receiued, or leſſe dueti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully regarded, then was, and is behoofeful? Ful hands can not apprehend any other thing, they are full already: fowle handes and ſoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the clay and brickeworke of ſinfull thoughtes and deedes, they are profane, and ſhould not preſume to touch his Iewels. Want of true knowledge in the worde of God, hath bred ſundry diſtemperatures and diſeaſes, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and hereſies in the body of Christes Church in this behalfe. When the writing is not knowen, the ſeales are leſſe or more then duely, and neuer aright eſteemed of the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant
<pb facs="tcp:25051:3"/>man. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the light of the Scriptures was hidde vnder the buſſhel of a ſtrange to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue, the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts alſo in the darke were most irreligiouſly contemned, ſuperſtitiouſly abuſed, carnally and groſly miſtaken. As good haue a ſeale to a blancke, as to a writing drawen in ſtrange characters and letters that cannot be read, or if read, yet vnderſtoode but of a fewe, and of them no further then it pleaſed the maſters of corrupt time at their leaſure, or begging Fryers for their gaine, to expounde in miſerable maner, to hungry, poore, and sterued ſoules. And then as good no bread at all, as ſo vile a prouender made of mixtures, eyther hard, or dowbaked and clammie: eyther they coulde not chewe it, or it coulde not nouriſhe them.</p>
            <p>Thus was the Lordes inheritance abuſed,<note place="margin">Iren. lib. 3. cap. 19.</note> famiſhed for want of true foode, or fedde as Irenee ſpeaketh, with lyme &amp; water, in ſtead of milke. The Deuil knewe he could not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile in the light, and therefore no ſleight of Satan euer like to this to deceiue men,<note place="margin">Mar. 12.24.</note> and ſlay ſoules. Whiles that Chriſtians were wiſe, they neuer ſought in pilgrimage from ſhrine to ſhrine,<note place="margin">S. P. Q. R. Beda.</note> neyther to Rome, nor to Ieruſalem, nor to any ſingular place vnder heaven, with
<pb facs="tcp:25051:3"/>obſeruation of the place,<note place="margin">Luke 17.20.</note> as if God were more tyed to this region, then to that, one or other. The true worſhippers worſhipped in ſpirit &amp; trueth. In trueth, without hypocriſie,<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.23.</note> and in ſpirite, without externall reſpectes. For as the Conye is acquainted with his owne burrowe &amp; ſafe rocke:<note place="margin">Prou. 30.26.</note> ſo Chriſtians then knew where to ſeeke, whither to runne, and howe to finde reſt in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for their ſoules. They aſked help alwayes of an able hande, trode the kings high way, knocked at the right gate, builded their houſe on the onely foundation: that is, they beleeued in Christ, called vpon God, were guyded by his ſpirite, truſted in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, hoped in his mercies manifeſtly layde abroad, and ſufficiently reuealed in his writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten worde,<note place="margin">Iohn 20.31.</note> and as certainely confirmed by the pledges of his will the holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes: whereof this treatiſe is intended for all ſuch as can be content to learne in fewe wordes of a ſimple teacher.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:25051:4"/>
            <head>Of the Sacraments <hi>in generall.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Sacrament is a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſigne to the eye, inſtituted of God to be continued in his Church, for the further aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and increaſe of ſpirituall graces in the faithful. Of which ſort is Baptiſme and the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,<note place="margin">Auguſt. e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. 118.</note> and onely theſe two, euen as they are ioyntly ſpecified by the Apoſtle to the Corinthians.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In the generall may bee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued theſe foure notes chiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The inſtitution to bee of God. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The ſigne viſible in ſenſe and reſemblance conuenient. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The graces ſecret and myſtical, but ſingular benefites to the faithfull man. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is the Churches duetie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> rightly to vſe and to enioy his ordinaunces as beſeemeth the Church of God.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb facs="tcp:25051:4"/>
               <note place="margin">The inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution.</note>
               <hi>1</hi> Concerning the inſtitution, as God onely is to be hearkened vnto in his ſayings, ſo muſt hee alone he followed in his wayes whereſoever he goeth before vs, and leadeth vs after him with the leaſt thread. Reaſon not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by faith, is a diſputing and a buſie miſtreſſe in the forge of mans braine, and ſhe will be leader in all things. Zeale like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe without knowledge, is a raſhe fire that licketh vp euery fonde deuiſe, feedeth and glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth her ſelfe on ſuperſtitious fancies, whereupon ambition in the man of pride,<note place="margin">The Papa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</note> taking her aduantage of the former two, hath ſtollen away the peoples heartes from their God vnder pretence of deuocion, but in deede ſuperſtition, enthroniſed her ſelfe in the conſciences of men, and exerciſeth a proude do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion ouer the Lordes inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb facs="tcp:25051:5"/>in his holy Temple. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding of the Apoſtle we haue learned a contrary leſſon,<note place="margin">Iam. 4.12.</note> that the onely Lawgiuer in Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael is the Lorde, becauſe he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone ſeeth the heart, whereunto the Lawe is principally propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſearcheth the reines, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth the inwarde parts, may commaunde, and will rewarde the good conſcience, will and is able to diſcerne right, and iudge uprightly, and hath denounced to take vengeance of the very ſoules of ſinners, wherein they cloſely, but chiefly offende. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may mortall men adde to, take from, or alter at pleaſure his wordes: and what are his Sacraments, but his wordes made viſible, and inueſted with ſignes of his owne ordayning?<note place="margin">Auguſt. 80. tract. in Ioh.</note> The examination of Iohns Baptiſme was on this maner: Whence is it?<note place="margin">Matt. 11.15.</note> from aboue, or
<pb facs="tcp:25051:5"/>from beneath? of God, or of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Yf from heauen, it was to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued: if from the earth, they might reiect it. For what is earth to heauen? man to God? our dreames to his worde? our dregges to his wine? Is there any taſte in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> white of an egge? What is chaffe to wheate, or glaſſe to a diamonde?<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.22.</note> Verily obedience is better then the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of good ententes, as they be termed. For will we honour him with the fatteſt cattell out of the ſtall, or worſhippe him in the calfe of pureſt golde? the one is but a beaſt that eateth hay, the other the workmanſhippe of the engrauers hands. By obeying, we offer vp our bodyes &amp; ſoules a reaſonable ſacrifice, wherein he is well pleaſed. Thereby we reuerence his maieſty, adore his wiſedome, ſubiect our willes to his will, reſt in his worde, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb facs="tcp:25051:6"/>no reckoning at all of any inſtitutions that merely touche the conſcience, but of his. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon with the bleſſed virgin we ſaye,<note place="margin">Iohn 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>What euer he commandeth, doe,</hi> and alſo what he hath not commaunded, we feare not to tranſgreſſe &amp; breake aſunder, as Samſon did thoſe greene withes and newe cordes.<note place="margin">Iudg. 16 9.</note> Wee knowe all ſuch witchecraftes the Lorde doeth vtterly abhorre. As for his Sacraments, they are his owne inſtitutions, hee marketh his ſheepe with his owne markes, writeth all with his own ſinger, ſealeth his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with his owne ſignet. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhoulde any preſume ſo much as to ſet to theſe his ſeales, but one ly ſuch as are called to ſo hye a calling, to be as it were the keepers of them to that ende ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed: much leſſe may men make newe ſeales of their owne
<pb facs="tcp:25051:6"/>deuiſing.</p>
            <p>When it pleaſed GOD to ſeale his promiſe made to Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham with the ſacrament of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion,<note place="margin">Gene. 17.</note> he calleth it his own couenant, and ſaide, <hi>It is I the Lorde,</hi> the author thereof. A par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular rule generally to bee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in euery Sacrament of either Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: <hi>It is I the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">The ſignes.</note>
               <hi>2</hi> In the ſecond place we are to take viewe of theſe ſeales, for they are viſible to the eye, as his voyce is audible to the eare.</p>
            <p>The drane water flie gazeth on euery faire flower, but ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth no honye as doth the Bee. The wandring ſight co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth litle of the excellencie of the ſeales. Before it was true to ſay, <hi>No inſtitution, no Sacrament:</hi> here we may as truely auouch, <hi>No ſigne, no Sacrament.</hi> For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole is made of all his partes, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Sacrament hath euer
<pb facs="tcp:25051:7"/>theſe two members, the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ſigne, and the inwarde grace, and without the ſigne is no grace ſacramentally ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at any time, neyther is the ſhew of a ſigne ſufficient, it muſt be material and able in a conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient proportion, to demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrate and declare to mans frayle capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, the grace implied and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified, as ſhall better appeare in the ſpecials afterwarde.</p>
            <p>The ſignes barely looked vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, they are baſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, earthly elements, common &amp; ordinarie: but put once y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſtampe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mettall, the ſeale to the waxe, the waxe and ſeale to the Lordes promiſe, the caſe is altered. For earthly, common and vſual elementes,<note place="margin">Iren. lib. 4. cap. 34.</note> that a litle before were, doe put nowe vpon them, and are endued with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine conſiderations: yet ſtil in ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce remaining y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, but
<pb facs="tcp:25051:7"/>in efficacy, vertue, ſeruice, ends, ſignification and repreſentation of graces, baſe thinges become beautifull and marueilous, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus ſequeſtred by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to ſo high and holy purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and therefore are vſualy ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the very names that the graces themſelues are called by. And this is alſo a common rule amongſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Fathers. See it ſo in examples out of the Scriptures. Circumciſion is the couenant, the Lambe the Paſſeouer, the Arke the Lorde, Baptiſme our buriall, Chriſt the rocke, the Bread his bodye, the Cup his blood, becauſe the analogie of theſe thinges is liuely, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion plaine, the ſignes ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficantly ordeyned of God: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus vttered, they more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect our fayth, and touch our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">The inuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble grace.</note>
               <hi>3</hi> Thirdly, the graces, (that is,
<pb facs="tcp:25051:8"/>(the inward parte of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) are, though ſingular in conſolation, yet ſecret in the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterye of their operation. God worketh howe he liſteth, and on whom he pleaſeth. The Iay fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth belowe, the carnall eye ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nothing but the barke and ryne of theſe things, bare water and bakers bread. Fayth flyeth higher, as the Eagle ſoareth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, and mounteth to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſelfe, where Chriſt ſitteth at the right hande of the father, the onely grounde worke, life and ſoule of all the Sacraments that euer were, or are in vſe. The ſong of Salomon is called the ſong of ſonges for his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie,<note place="margin">Nazianz. de Sacro. Bapt.</note> and God the God of gods for his puiſſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. In like maner, the graces we reape &amp; receiue by Chriſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacraments, (ſo great &amp; gracious are they) they may be termed graces of graces: as
<pb facs="tcp:25051:8"/>namely, remiſſion of ſinnes, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of righteouſneſſe, ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification of life, &amp; a ſpeciall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of our ſauiour Ieſus. Neither yet for all this (which is diligently to be noted) doe we tye or binde his goodnes ſo here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by that he muſt needes worke with, or can not worke without theſe meanes by his ſpirit, the ſaluation of them whom he had choſen and deſtinated to eternal life before all worldes. Many Iſraelites that died in the deſert when they could not trauaile if they had bene ſore and cut, were ſaued without circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſion. The thiefe that from the croſſe went ſtraight to heauen, was neuer otherwiſe baptized then in his owne confeſſion, faith, and peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Chriſt. Saluation is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kneaded into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dough, nor mingled w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water, no more then with the word, which is as Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom
<pb facs="tcp:25051:9"/>ſayeth more truely Chriſt,<note place="margin">Hierom. in Pſal. 147.3. cap. eccle.</note> but proceedeth from God, and is conueyed by ordinary meanes of eyther word or outward ſignes, where they are not contemned, but may conueniently he had, &amp; are reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly vſed as they ought.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">The vſe &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance.</note>
               <hi>4</hi> And this is the fourth and laſt point, the right vſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of the Sacraments. Phiſicke is not prepared, but to be receiued. As in the Reuelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, no man receiueth the white ſtone,<note place="margin">Reuel. 2.17.</note> but to whome it is giuen: ſo no man readeth the writing, but who receiueth it. The au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of the Sacraments, is God, the ſignes holy, the grace moſt holy. This Manna would be kept in a golden pot, and theſe iewels ſet in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pureſt golde. The gifte that is beſtowed, is moſt ſyncere, the ſtone white that is deliuered. And ought not then the hande to be a cleane hande,
<pb facs="tcp:25051:9"/>or rather the heart a pure heart, that receiueth ſuch pearles? GOD couenanteth to bee our God, ſhoulde we not accept the offer, &amp; reioyce in his couenant? Achaz in hypocriſie pretended he woulde beleeue God without a ſigne.<note place="margin">Eſai. 7.12.</note> Certainely ſo muſt we doe in deede many times. Balaam,<note place="margin">Nom. 23.19.</note> that ſaw leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his aſſe, ſaw ſo much, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Gods worde is ynough. <hi>Shall he ſpeake, and not doe?</hi> Yet when he offereth ſignes withal, to helpe forth our infirmities in faith according to his worde, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther naturall as the rainebow, or artificiall as the braſen ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, or miraculous, or Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental, or whateuer, if we then refuſe them, in ſteade of ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the fault of tempting him, we runne vpon the contempt of his heauenly wiſedome. <hi>Goe preach, baptize all nations.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 28.19.</note> This is a generall commaundement,
<pb facs="tcp:25051:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:25051:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:25051:11"/>and muſt be obſerued.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.24</note> 
               <hi>As often as ye eate this bread, and drinke this cuppe, ye ſhewe the Lordes death vntill his comming againe. As often,</hi> therefore often and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually: <hi>vntill his comming againe,</hi> therefore perperually muſt this Sacrament be continued in a godly remembrance of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes death.<note place="margin">Gen. 29.17. Deut. 34.7.</note> The olde ceremonies were weake ſighted like Leah, and therefore could not laſt euer. Moſes eyes were not dimme, vntill his dying day: ſo the force of Chriſtian Sacraments re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in their full vſe vntill the ende of the worlde.</p>
            <p>Their ſacraments, ſome were ſpeciall for place and perſon. In Paradiſe the tree of life was for the place,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.9. Iudg. 6.37. Eſa. 28.8.</note> the wette &amp; dryed fleece, the going backe of the dial, were perſonally to Gedeon and Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chias. And their chiefeſt Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, either extraordinary, as
<pb facs="tcp:25051:11"/>Manna and the rocke, ceaſed in the wilderneſſe: or ordinary, as circumciſion and the Paſſeouer, theſe alſo haue had their ende in the fulneſſe of time, when their wombe (as Cirill ſpeaketh) was deliuered of Chriſt, as a woman of her childe into the worlde. For Chriſt is come, and their cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies were of Chriſt to come, and when he came, they as ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes yeelded place at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the body. The difference of their Sacraments and ours conſiſteth in cleerenes of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and continuance of tynte. They caryed the former parte of the ſtaffe, &amp; we the hinder ende. Chriſt is borne betwixt vs both, but we that come after, haue the fuller viewe, and ſee directly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our face, they reſpectiuely and looking backe to that which they caryed and came after: and therefore more obſcurely then
<pb facs="tcp:25051:12"/>we. And nowe becauſe Chriſt is borne no more, liueth no more, dieth no more, &amp; becauſe all theſe thinges are plainely to the eye painted, &amp; poynted to with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in our Sacraments, ours are not henceforth to be changed any more, but are conſtant and perpetuall, and continually in all duety to be vſed and enioyed till his comming again to iudge the quicke and the dead in the laſt day.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of Baptiſme.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The nature of Baptiſme.</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Aptiſme is the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in water, wherby our ſinnes are clenſed, we clad with Chriſt, endued with his ſpirit, our names entred among the number of Chriſtian profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours,
<pb facs="tcp:25051:12"/>in the name of the bleſſed Trinitie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>Touching the inſtitution, whether it growe out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, or deſcende from aboue, be of men, or of God, being of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to be a Sacrament, and a Sacrament being already pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to be alwayes a diuine inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it is needleſſe to repeate or ſay further therein. Yet moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and aboue that, our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours owne example and general commandement, <hi>Go preach,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 3 15.</note> 
               <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize, &amp;c.</hi> are euident warrants, autentike, and ſpecial for proofe herein, that it is of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The forme of the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration.</note>The fourme of the action de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth what we receiue of God, and there withall enformeth vs what we owe and ought to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him againe. Through ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular mercie in the name of the Father, by like merit and mame of the Sonne, by the vertue of
<pb facs="tcp:25051:13"/>the Holy Spirite, name &amp; pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er thereof, we are made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of all the priuiledges, that may be incident to ſuch as ſhall be ſaued in the houſe &amp; Church of God. In whoſe lap, we are as it were newe borne, newe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, new apparelled, made new creatures in Ieſus Chriſt. Such is the forme, ſo great the force of this ſacrament.</p>
            <p>Wherein yf any man vpon a farther deſire to be inſtructed in the myſteries of his profeſſion,<note place="margin">The mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilous o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</note> muſe in minde, breake foorth, and ſay as Mary did to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel,<note place="margin">Luke 1.34.</note> 
               <hi>How may this be,</hi> that a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall element ſhoulde thus worke in ſpirituall things, that water touching the body ſhould clenſe the ſoule, that water in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fountaine where it is cleaneſt, hauing no ſuch operatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhould thus change and be changed in the Church and fonte whither
<pb facs="tcp:25051:13"/>it is brought from his ſpring? are theſe effectes naturall?<note place="margin">Exod. 11.25.</note> Of olde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waters of Marah were made ſweete, water in Cana,<note place="margin">Iohn. 2.8.</note> turned into wine,<note place="margin">Exod. 7.17.</note> the riuers of Nilus into bloode: and though euery of theſe mutations were mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilous in the ſight of the wiſeſt eye, yet in this caſe there is more done. Meere and bitter water in compariſon, is made exceeding ſweete, ſweeter then the fruite of the ripeſt &amp; pureſt grape: yea, yet more then this is done. Cold and vſual water, is really chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, truely, and indeede turned after the maner of Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, from a common moiſture, into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dewe of gods ſpirit, and into the bloode of the Lambe,<note place="margin">Reuel. 7.14.</note> wherein the ſoules of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Saintes are wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. For although it leaue not off to be water, but remaineth as before, a viſible ſigne, yet by the acceſſe of Gods worde, and
<pb facs="tcp:25051:14"/>the omnipotent power of his ſpirite, the Angell as it were deſcending vpon the poole in the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Iohn 5.4.</note> the change is greater, then mans wordes can expreſſe.</p>
            <p>By ſimilitudes framed and vttered to our capacities, fayth conceiueth conuenient inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; ſufficient comfort. Where the ſunne warmeth not, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is a ſterile and bare moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, neyther can it engender a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing without the heate and helpe of the ſpirite, that moued vpon the waters at their firſt creation.<note place="margin">Gen. 1.2.</note> For as it was then, ſo is it ſtill, &amp; as it was and is ſo in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> generation of things: ſo much more is it ſo in the regeneration of man. Water of it ſelfe cannot make a man, much leſſe a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man.<note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of the ſigne with the graces ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified.</note> The ſpirite of God is ſometymes ſayde to enflame and purifie like fire, and in this caſe to regenerate in water, to clenſe
<pb facs="tcp:25051:14"/>and waſhe like water. And as verily as cleare water clenſeth and cooleth the body: ſo, and as truely, the like graces by the bloode of Chriſt and his ſpirite, are wrought vpon the ſoule, by entrance into this bathe. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we may obſerue a further ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude, that as in waſhing pooles, when men goe into the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they doe off their aparell, and then enter the bath, and bathe their bodies: ſo in this the olde man is put off, Adams fig leaues throwen aſide, &amp; then with niter &amp; fullers ſope, nay rather with the bloode of the ſonne of God, all our former filthe is ſcoured a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. This diſſimilitude is in this ſimilitude, our former rags are neuer reſumed, as ſinners reſume their garmentes when they haue waſhed. Thoſe plaguy clothes that tooke ſtayne and infection from ſinfull Adam,
<pb facs="tcp:25051:15"/>we burie or we burne. The rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate man hath done away his former generation, dyeth to ſin, the gylte and dominion where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of lyeth as a dead body in the graue, and hath no more power ouer the creature which is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with the newe man, freed from Satan, accepted into ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and fauour in the familie of GOD, weareth the cloth of righteouſnes, and is apparelled as the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Reuelation with the ſonne of God.<note place="margin">Reue. 12.1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein notwithſtanding it is expedient, ſtill and euer to remember from what rocke we were he wen, on what ſtocke we grewe, what we haue loſt, and what wee haue founde, howe fowle we were, howe cleane we are, that taſting howe ſweete the Lord is, we may as it were, feele the difference betweene ſoote and ſugar, ſee and view the
<pb facs="tcp:25051:15"/>oddes betweene our crimoſin &amp; blood red ſinnes, and the ſnowe white innocencie we haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned in him.</p>
            <p>To compare the ſtate wherin we were by creation, &amp; then in nature corrupted, and nowe by grace and regeneration, were to compare an innocent lyfe, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued death, &amp; life euerlaſting together, that is, Paradiſe, hell, &amp; heauenly bliſſe, betwixt themſelues. For our caſe at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt was no worſe, afterward no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and in Chriſt betterthen e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer before.<note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> For as by one man came ſinne, and by ſinne death, which preſuppoſeth a former in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie, and life: ſo by the man Chriſt, much more excellent is the righteouſneſſe that is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to faith, imported by this Sacrament, and ſhalbe enioyed without end. As the firſt Adam, eating of the forbidden tree, he
<pb facs="tcp:25051:16"/>(ſuſteining the perſon of al man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde) by his diſobedience did ſet on edge his poſterities teeth: ſo the ſecond Adam trode the wine preſſe alone, and yet wee his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie alſo drinck neuer the leſſe of his wine. And here let no man ſay,<note place="margin">Prou. 9.2.</note> 
               <hi>I haue mixed mine owne wine,</hi> I haue compaſſed theſe thinges my ſelfe. Strength, if it leane to preſumption, is weaker then water, and the broken reede: and yet the ſtrongeſt thinges of man, are but meere weakneſſe, the puritie of nature, pollution, libertie of will, thraldome, and the merite of workes, a ſtayned cloute. And then if the clothe be ſo courſe, howe courſe is the liſt: or if the wooll be courſe, can the clothe be fine? Adam begate Seth,<note place="margin">Gen. 5.3.</note> and all his children in his owne likeneſſe. For as the man that is not, cannot beget him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe that he may haue a being:
<pb facs="tcp:25051:16"/>ſo man being naught, can neuer of him ſelfe beget any thing els, or him ſelfe to bee good againe. Why the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do we preſume? A puffe of pride bloweth out the candle that was lightened of another at the firſt, and cannot kindle it ſelfe the ſeconde time. The deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the Goſpel was not able to make payment for the ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand talentes,<note place="margin">Matt. 18.24.</note> and the more in debte in proceſſe of time, the more vnlike to come out of debt, albeit he ſayd as the aduerſaries of the trueth ſaye, if his Lorde would haue patience, he would pay and ſatiſfie all. The three pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rables in Saint Luke, tende all to this purpoſe,<note place="margin">Luke 15.</note> to ſhewe mans inhabilitie in euery reſpect, and the Lordes exceeding mercie al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together. The loſt groat lacketh ſenſe, the ſtrayed ſheep witte, the prodigall ſonne wiſedome. The woman lighteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> candle, ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth
<pb facs="tcp:25051:17"/>the houſe, ſeeketh diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The ſhepheard goeth out into the wilderneſſe, and bringeth home on his ſhoulders. And as for the waſtfull ſonne, God in his prouidence diſpoſed ſo, that by afliction and famin, he ſhould be taught and conſtrained to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne backe, making a moſt true confeſſion, that hee had ſinned againſt heauen and his father, and was no more worthie to bee called his ſonne. <hi>Had ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> and therefore nowe onely was to ſtande vpon grace &amp; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don: <hi>had ſinned againſt heauen,</hi> and therefore in earth vnfit and vnable to make ſatiſfaction: <hi>had ſinned againſt ſo louing a father,</hi> &amp; therefore vnworthy the name of a ſonne. Notwithſtanding, while he ſtoode yet a great waye off, his father ſawe him, and had compaſſion, ranne, (pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented him with mercie) fell on
<pb facs="tcp:25051:17"/>his necke and kiſſed him, killed the fatte calfe, put ſhoes on his feeete, and a ring on his finger, hyred muſicians, and called for the beſt robe, &amp; clad him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with that was vtterly deſtitute of al attire, except ſuch as Job ſpeaketh of:<note place="margin">Iob. 9.31.</note> 
               <hi>Mine owne clothes defile me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many excellent and rich or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments are layde together in one heape in the Prophet Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiel: embroydred works,<note place="margin">Ezech. 16.</note> brace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, ſilke, ſiluer, golde &amp;c. and all theſe God beſtowed on them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lay dead in their blood, whome he raiſed to life, circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed with his owne hand, dryed their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption with ſalte, waſhed their vncleannes with water, ſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and clad them with newe &amp; precious apparell, euen with Ioſephs party coloured coate, or rather with the Queenes gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of needle worke, which yet
<pb facs="tcp:25051:18"/>was not of her owne making.</p>
            <p>The olde purifyings did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figure out, and as it were made the firſt draught thereof: but the water of Baptiſme moſt liuely expreſſeth his mercy &amp; compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whoſe onely eye, &amp; no mans els, tooke pitie on vs then, when we lay, not wounded, but dead &amp; long dead in our ſinnes. In this water y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> litle fiſh &amp; humble Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian reſumeth life againe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lay gaſping &amp; dead on the ſhoare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. In this water y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Scorpion loſeth his venim,<note place="margin">Cypr. 4. lib. epiſt. 7.</note> and can not ſting. In this water, Sinne, Satan, the fleſh and the worlde lye floting &amp; drowned, as in the deluge in Geneſis,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.1. 1. pet. 3.21.</note> and red Sea in Exodus, where Noah y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of righteouſneſſe and a few with him were ſaued in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Arke, which after a ſorte was a figure of Baptiſme. The Iſraelites went through on dry foot, Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rao
<pb facs="tcp:25051:18"/>and all his hoſte drowned in the red ſea. But for all this, this is true in the letter of theſe ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and certaine in the trueth of a farther meaning, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> though Noah eſcaped drowning, yet he was ouercome afterward with wine: though the Egyptians were ouerwhelmed al, yet there remained other enemies in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert: neither did Iſrael ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes enter the promiſed land, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out further labour &amp; fightes firſt had with ſundry and diuers nations.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Hierom. ad Ocean. Aug. retract. lib. 1. cap. 7. Ephe. 5.25. Rom. 7.</note> In this Sacrament, though generally iniquity be pardoned, and ſinne drowned, and wee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, yet for all this, al infirmitie is not quite aboliſhed, wee are waſhed al,<note place="margin">Ioh. 13.10.</note> but our feete (ſuch are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wayes wherin we tread) neede daily and continuall waſhing. The effect of Baptſme worketh not in a moment, but by litle &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:25051:19"/>litle, as the leauen ſeaſoneth the whole fiue peckes at length. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a great ſickneſſe, ſtrength is not recouered but in continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of time: the wound is hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, but it muſt be ſkinned ouer alſo. When this mortalitie ſhall change for immortality, corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion put on incorruption, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde Phenix be made a newe, then, &amp; neuer till then perfectly, euery wrinckle ſhall be made plaine, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſpot waſhed, &amp; euery teare wiped away from our face, our nakedneſſe couered ouer, or quite done away, and we preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted blameleſſe to the iudgement ſeat of God.<note place="margin">Col. 1.22.</note> In the meane time, while our dwelling is in this vale of miſerie &amp; houſes of clay, it is our continuall duetie daily more and more to contende and proceed from faith to faith, from ſtrength to ſtrength, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vertue to vertue, crucifying the old ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:25051:19"/>hauing ſtill recourſe to that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall graunt of pardon we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in Baptiſme at the firſt, remiſſion of ſinnes in the death of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Not that this Sacrament be eftſoones repeated &amp; reiterated againe in fact,<note place="margin">Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtes.</note> but afreſh recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in faith, godly meditation,<note place="margin">Auguſt. 11. tract. in Ioh. vterus non repetitur.</note> &amp; humble prayer. The father doth not often begette his ſonne, but the ſonne remembring that hee was begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a louing father, bethinketh himſelf, conſidereth his duetie, increaſeth in pietie, reuerent awe &amp; obedience. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſeede one and the ſame graine is often ſowen, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once ſowen in due ſeaſon, it bringeth foorth his fruite. The harueſt of mans perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is not in this worlde. The ſowing which is once, and the growing time which is ſtill, is here: full ripeneſſe is fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d els where.<note place="margin">Auguſt. de Ieiunio.</note> 
               <hi>Imus
<pb facs="tcp:25051:20"/>nondum peruenimus:</hi> we are but in the way to heauen, going on and trauailing till we come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, euen growing toward it, &amp; groning after it. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> midway, no man ſpinneth ſo euen a thred that neuer breaketh, treadeth ſo right that neuer trippeth. For beſides diuers actuall ſinnes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ineuitable ſinne of concupiſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which luſteth againſt the ſpirit, is left ſtill as a ſting in the Bee, notwithſtanding his hony and diuers graces by grace receiued. The aduerſaries to the trueth, in their Couent at Trent,<note place="margin">1. Decr. 5. Seſſ. Cat. Tri. de. bap. ſacr.</note> and in their Treatiſe of Baptiſme, woulde extenuate &amp; make light of it, ſaying, it is not in any wiſe ſinne, except it be conſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted vnto. Saint Iames teaching what will be the ende of ſinne,<note place="margin">Iacob. 1.14.</note> ſayeth, that concupiſcence te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pteth, dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth and entiſeth to (actual and externall) ſinne: and is this no
<pb facs="tcp:25051:20"/>ſinne? It is the mother of ſinne, and are not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mother &amp; daughter both of one nature? Againe the very name <hi>Luſt</hi> carieth with it a kinde of conſent, deſire, and will to ſinne. But ſuppoſe, that by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the external acte of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning be reſtrained, what then? God conſidereth the hearte, and he with all our ſtrength, power and faculties, is to be ſerued: the leaſt defaulte in any parte of our inward parts, is an offence and ſinne againſt his Maieſtie. But doeth conſent or diſſent, make our luſtes eyther ſinnes or no ſinnes? Is not an enemie an enemie if he be conquered? Is not rebellion treaſon, if it be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented? Is not ſedition ſedition, if it be repreſſed? Is luſt no ſinne if it be kept in? Is fire no fire, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it flame? What neede many words? Doth not the Apoſtle in expreſſe words, ſundry times cal
<pb facs="tcp:25051:21"/>concupiſcence ſinne, becauſe it hindereth the good he woulde, &amp; helpeth forward y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euil he would not? They ſay the Apoſtle ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth improperly: a wonder. He that framed the eare, made the eye, faſhioned the tongue, ſhall he not heare, doth he not ſee, can he not ſpeake as properly as the children of men? were there no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but this, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are taught to pray with ſighes as S. Paul doth againſt this temptation, it were ſufficient &amp; proofe plaine y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is ſinne. For in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it be not, we cofeſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> where it is, it ſhoulde not be, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is, it is ſinne, eſpecially being forbidden in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lawe. A li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle feeling of a good conſcience, might take away all controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie in the queſtion, as hath bene wel declared not long ſince.<note place="margin">Reply to the cenſure 5. articulo.</note> And thou, O man, which haſt a ſence what ſinne is, ſubmitte thy ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:25051:21"/>vnder the power of Gods hand, powre forth thy ſoule in prayſe to ſo mercifull a Lorde, who hath forgiuen the gylte of this and al other thine offences, who bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them dayly in a bundell, &amp; will one day drowne or dye them all to an other colour in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blood of his ſonne, whereof thy Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is a ſure ſeale.</p>
            <p>This knowledge and confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion belongeth to al people, from the cleauer of the woode, to the Prince and counſeller, from the Cedars of Libanus, to the Hyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoppe of the wall backe agayne: high and lowe, rich and poore, old and yong, one with another, without reſpect of perſons, they are the Lordes equally. Ancient men muſt not forget who was hee that tooke them from their cradle, and caried them along in his armes to their gray heares.<note place="margin">Eſa. 46.4.</note> Children muſt learne that they
<pb facs="tcp:25051:22"/>alſo are conteyned in his coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. Iohn was ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctified in his mothers wombe,<note place="margin">The bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</note> Samuel in his childhoode conſecrated vnto the Lorde,<note place="margin">Mar. 10.14.</note> Children brought to Chriſt that he might lay handes on them. Bring wee then alſo our children, that Chriſt may bleſſe them in his owne inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">Gen. 17.12.</note> as of old God did y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed infantes of eight dayes age. Delayes may be dangerous and are needleſſe,<note place="margin">Auguſt. de verb. a poſt. hom. 9.</note> the vſage is an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient rule of fayth. It is true, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> not the lacke,<note place="margin">Bern. ad Hugon. Epi. 77.</note> but the neglecte of the Sacrament doeth hurt: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware then of contempt. Chriſt baptizeth with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fire: with the ſpirite, that is, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual graces he endueth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who in faith &amp; thankfulneſſe obſerue his word, receiue his ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, are ingraffed into him, &amp; growe vp in him as liuely bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true vine.<note place="margin">Iohn 15.1.</note> Againe hee baptizeth
<pb facs="tcp:25051:22"/>with his ſpirite,<note place="margin">Luk. 3.16.</note> able to diſcerne hypocrites, &amp; with fire red hote, readie to conſume al chaffe &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, as both the ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Popiſhe, and alſo the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Anabaptiſt, that eyther preſume, or peruert, or any way pollute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right vſe of this his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordinance, which to the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent receiuer, is the bath of his regeneration in Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> badge of his profeſſion, and the bonde of brotherly loue in the houſe of our God.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.3.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of the Supper.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Leuits dutie was to prepare the people to the worthy recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the Paſſeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.<note place="margin">2. Chro. 35.6</note> In place whereof, hath ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy &amp; blood of our Sauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, with ſemblable, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie, and conuenient prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:25051:23"/>thereunto.<note place="margin">Chriſoſt. in 1. Cor. hom. 24.</note> For if it were a princes ſacred body, or but pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple garment onely (the matter whereof is wormes thread, &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour no better then the dead fiſhe blood) yet were it not raſhly to be abuſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vnwaſhed or vncleane handes. How much the more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerent then ought y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> receiuing of theſe holy myſteries of Chriſts body and blood to be of all them that know what it is to ſtand in awe that they offend not? Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let a man examine himſelfe, ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.28</note> &amp; <hi>ſo</hi> let him eat of this bread, &amp; drinke of this cup. Euen <hi>ſo,</hi> &amp; therfore if not ſo, not at all. Better to abſtaine, then to come together for the worſe.</p>
            <p>As the print in waxe is more fitly receiued and fully expreſſed, when the waxe is wrought and warmed firſt: ſo like wiſe the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of this Sacrament is more liuely felt and ſeene, when wee
<pb facs="tcp:25051:23"/>repayre thereunto with prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red mindes, wel inſtructed, and throughly examined.</p>
            <p>In which examination, two poyntes chiefely are obſerued, wherof the one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerneth faith, the other loue. Fayth, to be ſetled in our heartes towardes God: Loue, to be ſhe wed to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor. The latter procedeth out of the former, and both from the ſpirit of God. Faith receiueth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe by hearing and prayer:<note place="margin">Rom. 10.17. Luk. 17.5. Mark. 9.24.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord increaſe our faith.</hi> Loue and faith iointly are ſtirred vp and ſtrengthened by repentance, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worthy repayring to, &amp; recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing at the Lordes table. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ariſeth theſe three, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents in this examination, <hi>aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red faith, brotherly loue, earneſt repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faith</hi> directeth in knowledge. <hi>Loue</hi> is occupied in tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfulnes to God, and good doing toward
<pb facs="tcp:25051:24"/>men. <hi>Repentance</hi> euer in ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther amendeth what is omitted or done amiſſe, and craueth par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don with humble minde and ful purpoſe, not to offend in the like againe. All which dueties (as I take) may be rightly conſidered according to the times, wherin eyther we are to receiue, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently receiue, or haue receiued the Sacrament. The firſt is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a <hi>Preparation</hi> vnto the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond, a <hi>meditation</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the third, a chriſtian <hi>conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation</hi> that muſt enſue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon.</p>
            <p>In preparing our ſelues is required,<note place="margin">Preparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we knowe of whom, what, and in what order wee muſt receiue.</p>
            <p>It ſeemeth to be recorded as a comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dation,<note place="margin">Of whom we receiue 1. Sam. 1.23.</note> that Anna nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her owne ſonne: in which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect among infinite others, the loue of God exceedeth all loue.
<pb facs="tcp:25051:24"/>Wherein as he ſpareth no coſt, ſo hee vndertaketh any care,<note place="margin">Plutar de in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitu. lib.</note> which nice and vnnatural mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers refuſe to do, putting forth their infantes to bee nurſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade, without neede or cauſe. Our God doeth not ſo, neyther needeth he ſo to doe,<note place="margin">Iſai. 49.15.</note> his breaſts are neither ſore, nor drye at any time. Of his owne good will he begat vs againe in baptiſme, &amp; ſo will he ſtil feede and bring vs vp to a full age, &amp; perfect grouth in Chriſt. Sufficient or abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant prouiſion for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in his wiſedome hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſpirite being ſtew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard of all, and as it were diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buter and caruer at the board.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What we receiue.</note>And to come to the ſeconde poynt, what we receiue. The meate of this table, is the very death of Chriſt, the Lambe of God, that taketh away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſinnes of the world. The ſtory and inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution
<pb facs="tcp:25051:25"/>whereof, is recorded by three Euangeliſtes,<note place="margin">Matt. 26.26. Mark. 14.22 Luk. 22.19.</note> and againe commented vpon by the holy ghoſt at large in the former Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of S. Paul to the Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: where the Apoſtle begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the matter with a faithful ſaying,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.23</note> 
               <hi>That which I haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of the Lorde, I haue deliuered you.</hi> For otherwiſe, if he came with offers of his own deuiſing, himſelfe raught the Galathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans what his entertainement ought to be:<note place="margin">Gal. 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>Let him be accuſed, though he were an Angell of God from heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord Ieſus, that night y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was betrayed, tooke bread: and when he had giuen thanks, he brake, and ſayde, <hi>Take, eate, this is my bodie which is broken for you: this doe in remembrance of me,</hi> In like maner the cup, &amp;c. <hi>For as often as ye ſhall eate this bread and drinke this cup, ye ſhewe
<pb facs="tcp:25051:25"/>the Lordes death till he come a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gaine.</hi> Wherein wee ſee euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what Chriſt did, &amp; alſo in due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie what we muſt do. In the viſible ſignes which he tooke, of bread that he brake, wine that he powred foorth, and in deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both to be taken, eaten and drunke, he manifeſtly decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red two things: the one, that he woulde immediately make an oblation for the redemption of mankinde vpon the altar of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe: the other that for euer he woulde be the euerlaſting foode of their ſoules, his body to be the bread of life, his precious blood to be their comfortable drinke, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Phyſicke of immortalitie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ignat. epiſt. ad Eph.</note> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruatiue againſt all euill. The ſacrifice &amp; oblation he inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, is plaine by theſe words, <hi>Which is broken,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.28.</note> 
               <hi>which is ſhed for many for remiſſion of ſinnes.</hi> Euen is <hi>broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſhed,</hi> becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houre wherin
<pb facs="tcp:25051:26"/>he ſhould be betrayed and ſuffer, drewe nigh and was at hande, That he would be their foode, is proued cleerely, in that hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to <hi>take, &amp; eate, this is my body.</hi> Nowe by the way, out of theſe two notes, may be noted two forcible reaſons, againſt the ſacrifice pretended in the maſſe.</p>
            <p>They are lately delighted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> motiues and demandes, may I aſke them this queſtion? Doe they thinke a ſinfull prieſt can do more at his maſſe, then the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God did at his ſupper? I hope they will not prefer a meere man before Chriſt God and man, the Sauiour of the worlde. And if ſo, then may they ſee their prieſt can make no ſacrifice: for Chriſt himſelfe when he ſate at boorde with his diſciples, made none, but declared what he meante to make. For and if he had ſo done y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Thurſday at night, what nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="tcp:25051:26"/>he the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue ſuffered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day at noone? againe, he willeth vs to <hi>take</hi> and <hi>eate,</hi> and feede on him. He offreth himſelfe to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued of vs, not to be offered by vs to his Father. That was his owne proper and perſonall due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. But to leaue to ſpeake hereof, our dewtie is with thankfulnes to feede on the food he offreth vs, euen to eate and drinke him, to partake his bleſſed body and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious blood. Wherein, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to miſtake and mingle the ſignes, and the things ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſedly without differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, were as Aug. ſayth,<note place="margin">De doct. Chr.</note> a miſerable thraldome to the very ſoule of a Chriſtian man. Chriſtes wordes be plaine. He tooke bread, after thankes giuen he breake &amp; gaue bread: for what he toke, he brake, and what he brake, he gaue, and therefore he gaue bread. For the Apoſtle ſaith he brake bread, and
<pb facs="tcp:25051:27"/>that he calleth his body, and ſo concerning the cuppe: for after a ſort, to ſpeake of one, is to ſpeake of both. Marie tooke Chriſt to haue bene a Gardiner,<note place="margin">Iohn 20.15.</note> but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries take a portion of bread to be Chriſt. The true profeſſors ſay and beleeue, that this ſaying of the Lorde, <hi>This bread is my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> hath a ſpirituall and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental meaning, &amp; otherwiſe to auouch, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a piece of bread (for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is bread, is proued) or els which is all one, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the ſhewe of bread is li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terally very Chriſt, is a mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous kinde of ſpeaking, vtterly impoſſible, &amp; altogether blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous. For if bread, or the ſhew of bread, or that which was bread, be called Chriſt properly, and w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out figure of ſpeache: without all controuerſie, as properly and as truely (but there is no ſhewe of trueth in ſo groſſe errors) bread was borne of the virgin Marie,
<pb facs="tcp:25051:27"/>bread was crucified on the croſſe, bread ſhal iudge the quicke and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead, and a piece or a fancye of bread is the Sauiour of the worlde, the ſonne of God, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde perſon in Trinitie, God himſelfe, &amp; the Lord of life. In ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſo ſtrangely, haue our vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural countrey men writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and one more fondly then the reſt,<note place="margin">Sand. in his Manhu.</note> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting an Epiſtle dedicatorie to his Lorde and God, vnder the formes of bread and wine in the Sacrament. Thus it fareth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe men by the iuſt iudgement of the Almighty God, who haue giuen him ouer, &amp; he them, that becauſe they woulde not beleeue the trueth, they ſhoulde ſtill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue lyes without ende, chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the glorie of the immortall God, into the ſimilitude of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt creatures, beſides all ſenſe, reaſon, and congruence of fayth. Chryſoſtome, writing vpon La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bans
<pb facs="tcp:25051:28"/>complaint, where he ſaith to Iacob,<note place="margin">Gene. 31.30.</note> 
               <hi>Why haſt thou ſtolen my gods?</hi> what, ſaith that father, what perfect folly is this? Are thy gods ſuch, as they may be ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len? or art thou not aſhamed in ſo ſaying? Semblably, what a Chriſt haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aduerſaries made and imagined? is Chriſt made of bread? ground with teeth, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the bitte of mouth, and ſtolen away ſometime of the ſely mouſe? or are they not aſhamed of theſe carnal &amp; fleſhly more the Capernaitical groſſe dreames, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> profite nothing? nay rather dread they not in hearte &amp; ſoule, to ſay as they haue ſayde to the cake in the Prieſts hands,<note place="margin">D. Har. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futa. of the Ap. pag. 94. Pointz in his Teſti. cap. 3. Briſt. Mot. 26.</note> 
               <hi>Thou art my maker,</hi> and to the wine in the chalice, <hi>Thou art my Lord and my God,</hi> by thee alone and nothing elſe, I hope to be ſaued</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Biſh. Cran. to Winch. and Biſh. Iewel to Hard. &amp;c.</note>The iuſt confutatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of which ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſpeaches, hath bin vnder taken &amp; diſcharged of moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb facs="tcp:25051:28"/>learned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in our Engliſh tongue. My purpoſe is onely in a worde, to giue warning to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſimple of this myre, wherin they ſee thoſe dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ken men, ſeruants to their owne deuiſes, thus to wallowe, plunge, and tumble themſelues vp and downe.</p>
            <p>There are others, who albeit they are not ſo farre gone out of the way, yet they treade not the true hie way, in euery reſpecte. As they confeſſe Chriſt to be in heauen, and yet they worſhippe no heauen, but Chriſt, ſitting there at the right hand of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: ſo ouer much reſting vpon the bare letter of the words, they ſuppoſe onely a conioyned pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in the bread, and no more. They go no further, neither doe they adore the bread, thogh they thinke Chriſt conſubſtantially to be therein. When they are vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with the vndouted article of
<pb facs="tcp:25051:29"/>the Creed, wherby we beleeue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſcenſion of our Sauiour, ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> replie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt being God, may be euery where. Others al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together abſurdly ſay, he auen it ſelfe is euery where. Were it not but that ſomewhat might bee learned, belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging neceſſarily to this treatiſe by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way, it were a folly to refute follies. Verely as Chriſt is perfect God, ſo is hee perfect man, &amp; the properties of both natures entire in one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. We may not build his deity, &amp; deſtroy his humanity. Who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his manhood, is gone from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, taken vp to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, aſcended on hie, ſitteth and maketh interceſſion there: the heauens muſt conteine him, till the laſt tymes, and then &amp; thence we look for his comming again. Neither can all this be a meere ſuppoſed vaniſhing out of ſight, but a locall departure: becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:25051:29"/>the place is ſet downe whence he went, and whither he aſcended, and that he ſhall come againe. I <hi>leaue the worlde and goe to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 16.28.</note> and <hi>he ſhall ſo come againe from heauen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 1.11.</note> And here to dreame y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> heauen is euery where, were a madneſſe. For then Chriſt had bene in heauen before already, &amp; ſo what needed he to departe and aſcende and goe hence? and if earth were heauen, the wicked and earthely minded men were moſt in heauen. And not onely they but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very damned ſpriits in hell were in heauen alſo: for hell is ſome where, and they ſay heauen is euery where. And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> where were that great Chaos, that is ſpoken of in the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.23.26.</note> betwixt Abrahams ioyes in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen aboue, and the riche mans torments in hel beneath? There is a kinde of ſpirite which is not driuen away but with prayer &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:25051:30"/>faſting, to the end to praye more earneſtly, the Lorde if it be his will, ende all quarels, eſpecially about this ſacrament of vnitie, open the eyes of all thoſe who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they be, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſeeke vaine ſhiftes and fond detriſes, to the end one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to exclude one conuenient &amp; v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual figure, which neceſſarily go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the nature of a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; agreeth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the canons of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian beleefe, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out the which our beleefe concerning the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Chriſt, can neuer ſtande. For if hee be perfect man (as we beleeue) like to his brethren in al thinges,<note place="margin">Heb. 1.17.</note> ſinne excepted, being but one man, hee can bee but in one place at one tyme. The want of ſinne both not extende a bodye to pluralities of places: for then euery man, as hee hath leſſe or more ſinne, ſhoulde bee ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye in fewer &amp; moe places ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly. But theſe thinges in
<pb facs="tcp:25051:30"/>ſight are but vanities. Wherfore Chriſt according to his humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, is and muſt bee in one place at once, and no moe, and that is in heauen.</p>
            <p>Nowe then in earth, what do wee receiue, while wee receiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sacrament? certainely Chriſt Ieſus, the land and the fruite, Chriſt and the vertues of his life and death, and of what euer hee did. But he is in heauen, and we in earth, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſtance is great. Faith hath an eye, an hande &amp; a wing, wherby it pearceth, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth and flyeth vp to heauen it ſelfe. To fayth, thinges abſent are preſent, thinges diſtant are conioyned, thinges ſecret are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, vnſeene are viſible, impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble are eaſy. As verely as bread both ſerue for the ſtrength of the body, and wine for the comforte thereof: ſo and as certainly to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in warde man in fayth, Chriſt is
<pb facs="tcp:25051:31"/>bread to the ſoule, and wine to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> minde, and we miſtically made one in him, and hee with vs, dwell in him, and hee in vs, feede on him, and he our ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all foode. And this is that which we receiue at his boarde. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, our knowledge is in parte, and therefore our ſpeach is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect. Thoſe harder partes of the Lambe that could not be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, were conſumed with fire: euen ſo, if there be any thing (as I graunt to me there is) which wordes cannot expreſſe, a godly mans faith may better compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, and in heart conceiue, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I vtter. It is not bare bread &amp; a ſip of wine (as ſcorners ſpeake) that we receiue, but truely, &amp; in deed very Chriſt. And wheras it is ſo, let vs go on &amp; ſee how ſuch a gheſt ought to be entertained.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>riſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ght to recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>Prepare the chamber of thy ſoule, ſweepe the houſe of thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,
<pb facs="tcp:25051:31"/>yeeld vp the keyes of thy heart, proſtrate thy ſelfe in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, open wide the gates of faith, that the king of glory may enter therein.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Berengaria<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his recanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>The aduerſary whetteth his teeth, openeth his mouth, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ready his belly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he might chewe and ſwallow vp his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker. <hi>Meate for the belly, &amp; the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for meate, and the Lord ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them both.</hi> O my brethren, who euer you are, this heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly foode is not <hi>Let vs eate and drinke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>and to morrowe we ſhall dye.</hi> Here is neither veniſon for Iſahac, nor a Kid for Tobi, nor Quailes in the deſert, nor wine in boules, nor wine in flagons. Who euer eateth of this celeſtial Manna, &amp; drinketh of this ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual rocke which is Chriſt, ſhal not only walke in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrength of it fourty dayes and fourty nights as the Prophet did, but ſhal liue
<pb facs="tcp:25051:32"/>for euer with God.</p>
            <p>Wherfore the wicked and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly,<note place="margin">Faith.</note> haue no part nor portion therein. They eate the bread of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde, but not the Lorde the bread of life, becauſe they want the hand of fayth to receiue him. He that eateth Chriſt, ſhall liue by the meanes of Chriſt: but the life of the wicked is no life, &amp; in their death is eternal da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation.</p>
            <p>The aduerſaries care li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle what Iewels they caſt to ſwine, what vncleane beaſtes they driue into the Lordes pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, howe fine manchet they throwe to very dogges. There is no communicating of Chriſt, but in the true communion of Chriſt. One head is head but of one body: and though it giueth ſome heate by meanes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heart to a rotten member that is not yet cut off, yet it giueth life only to the ſound partes. The chaffe
<pb facs="tcp:25051:32"/>and huſke of corne receiueth a kind of humour, but the fat and heart of the ſeede onely nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth the wheate, and not the chaffe. The bare name of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie, the barke and letter of the word, the outward eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the Sacrament, are after a ſort in common to all: but true Chriſtianitie, a good vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and the inward grace of theſe thinges, are proper to the godly, and to none other. The humor y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the wicked receiue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the roote, ſerueth to encreaſe a great deale more chaffe, and the chaffe to nouriſh a bigger fire, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is due for a greater quantitie thereof. If it were otherwiſe, howe eaſely might the Apoſtle be anſwered, and howe ſoone put to ſilence, when he aſketh what part &amp; communion,<note place="margin">2. Cor<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 6.19.</note> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a good ſocietie, is there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the faithfull and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels?
<pb facs="tcp:25051:33"/>Forſooth they haue a fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip in the participation of Chriſt in the Sacrament. No, the ſpirit of God ſuffreth no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plye.</p>
            <p>The Communion in this ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is two folde. In reſpect of the giuer, and the duetie of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuers, toward him alone and amongſt themſelues onely. The gift of communicating him, is offered by grace: for who euer gaue him firſt, that it may be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him againe?<note place="margin">Cyril. lib. 4. cap. 17. in Iohn.</note> And he is recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by faith: ſend forth thy faith, &amp; thou haſt taken holde on him. The communitie which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> receiuers themſelues, is by charitie &amp; loue. Loue ſeeketh not his owne,<note place="margin">Loue.</note> and that is loue in deede, which is betwixt bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren then when a man loueth another,<note place="margin">Auguſt. de temp. ſer. 256.</note> either becauſe Chriſt is in him, or to the ende Chriſt may be in him. And this is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb facs="tcp:25051:33"/>poynt, which muſt alſo be brought to the worthy recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of Chriſt. Some are pale with faſting, and blewe with enuie, tame their body as it were a wilde horſe, and ride out of the way whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue done. <hi>When you come together, there are diſſentions among you,</hi> ſayth S. Paul to the Corinthians, <hi>euery man maketh his ſupper, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he come to the Lords Supper, no man tarieth one for another.</hi> Ye haue made a priuate matter of the publike liturgie &amp; church duetie. What ſhall I ſay? <hi>ſhall I praiſe you? in this I praiſe you not.</hi> And his not prayſing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, was a marueilous diſprayſe. The rich diſdained the poore, the poore enuied the rich, the head would not direct the foote, one member was at variance with an other, and yet euery member hath an intereſt in
<pb facs="tcp:25051:34"/>the next, &amp; ſo the laſt and euery one eche in another, and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther among them ſelues. The candle muſt not hide it ſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a buſhel, nor flaſh in another mans eies, being proud that one hath lighted it, and litle conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that it ſelf might be burnt or put out, and another lighted in his roome. Veſſels conteine water not for them ſelues, but for others, &amp; if they refuſe their duetie, though they are ful, they may be emptied. There is a more excellent way, if men did walke therein, and if euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> woulde cary his brothers burden. The elme vnderproppeth the vine, &amp; the vine is without prickes, and hurteth not, but is an ornament to the elme. The foot beareth the head and body, &amp; the head gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them both. Shall an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewe wound an Hebrewe,<note place="margin">Exod. 1.13.</note> the fathers ſonne his brother and
<pb facs="tcp:25051:34"/>the ſonne of his mother, the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant his fellowe? The worlde that is w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out, hateth vs ynough, though we y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are within, hate not our ſelues. The God of loue enflame our coldeneſſe in chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, mollifie our hard and cruell hearts, qualifie and ſoften all rough and vneuen wayes and dealing. Why? are we not bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of the ſame parent, of God in his Church? ſubiectes of one King the Lorde? and vnder one Queene a gracious Lady? are we not cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trymen and fellowes in one familie? haue we not the ſame hope and ſpirite? haue wee not the ſame enemies, friendes, faith and the foode of faith, the word and Sacraments?<note place="margin">Cor. Tacit. in vita Iul. Agric.</note> Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Tacitus reporteth that the olde Britons were eaſely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, becauſe they vſed no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation nor common conſent in matters. The Madianites
<pb facs="tcp:25051:35"/>killeth one an other. Ioſias fought an vnneceſſary battell, &amp; dyed in the field. It is good to be wiſe and patient, wiſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, patient &amp; ſilent in trifles, when a man ſhall but digge in the fire, &amp; the ſparkles flie in his face and no good done. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe if a venimous ſpider come in the way, who will not ſet foot vpon it? Yf the cauſe be the Lordes, and the quarell good, &amp; thy calling according, it is good fighting theſe battels. <hi>Striue for the trueth for life, defende iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice vnto death.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccle. 4.2.</note> In this caſe the white liuered ſouldier that fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a froſt ſhall be couered with ſnow. If euery heare were a life, and euery life a thouſand liues, ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter them all for him that gaue them all. But againe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dayes of peace, where peace may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed with leſſe a doe, what wiſe man woulde be hanged in
<pb facs="tcp:25051:35"/>heare of his own fancie, or fal as Saul did vpon his owne ſword. He that loueth daunger, ſhal pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in trouble and no man pitie him, and the meeke ſhall poſſeſſe the earth.</p>
            <p>A gentlewoman of Lacede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monia,<note place="margin">Plutar. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Colo.</note> and Diotorus his wife did alwayes fall out at the table and varie, becauſe the one loued oyle, and the other butter, and yet the qualities of butter and oyle were not much diuerſe.</p>
            <p>Charitie doeth couer malice, enuie and hatred doeth vncouer as the boyſterous Northwinde all imperfections, and natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men are giuen to prie in at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens windowes, to beate duſt of their coates, &amp; find motes in their eyes. But Saint Paul ſaith, Let euery man proue him ſelfe and not other men, and ſo let him come to this Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. When Chriſt foretolde that one
<pb facs="tcp:25051:36"/>of his diſciples ſhoulde betray him, euery one of them began to aſke him,<note place="margin">Mar. 14.19.</note> 
               <hi>Is it I?</hi> not is it he or he, but euery one was deſirous to proue him ſelfe and know, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were he, <hi>Is it I?</hi> they were not like him that ſaide,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.4.</note> 
               <hi>Brother ſuffer me to take foorth the mote out of thine eye.</hi> And doe we call them brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whoſe good name we ſeeke to take from them in obiecting motes and faultes? A mote is a litle fault, and a beame is a great faulte, and neither great nor litle ſhould be ſuffered, eſpecially in the eye. Yet euery man is not a fit Phyſition, the eye is a tender parte, and maye as ſoone take hurt as good, if there be not great diſcretion ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. Let the publike miniſter proue all, and the priuate man proue him ſelfe, and ſo in fayth and loue let vs all in one repair to the Sacrament of vnitie
<pb facs="tcp:25051:36"/>which as goates milke ſhoulde breake and mollifie the ſtonie hearts of men,<note place="margin">Plin lib. 20. prooe. &amp; lib. 3.7. cap. 4.</note> as rayne alaieth great windes, &amp; as Dauids mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke aſſwaged Sauls mela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and euill ſpirite. And yet when all this is done, the beſt men are men ſtill, and the beſt earth is earth euer, and will beare nettles and brambles and prickes. Fleſh is fraile in faith, blood imperfect in loue, ſeetheth and boyleth with a litle fire and vpon a ſmall occaſion,<note place="margin">Repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance.</note> &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>repentance</hi> alwayes in ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is moſt requiſite, which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companying with <hi>faith</hi> her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and <hi>loue</hi> her ſiſter, war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth and cheriſheth them both, who otherwiſe waxe wanne and colde and looſe their force.</p>
            <p>Yf any man deeme Chriſtes death vnſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſuppoſe his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice needeth renuing, imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth any other interceſſours re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite,
<pb facs="tcp:25051:37"/>doubteth of his kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, beleueth not his word, theſe are great wants of <hi>faith,</hi> and he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer proued himſelfe, that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth with this minde to the Lordes boorde, where theſe thinges are or ſhould be felt &amp; fed vpon. Here <hi>Repentance</hi> is requiſite to helpe fayth. Againe, if any man haue any thing againſt his brother, or his brother againſt him, let him go firſt and be reconciled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he eate and drincke the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramente, which is of vnitie in Chriſt Ieſus. Thus examining his conſcience as before, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging his ſinnes in his ſight, aſke pardon with ſighes &amp; teares, becauſe he eyther diſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, or diſobeyed, and ſo diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſo gratious a God, ſo merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a father, ſo perfecte a Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, that had commanded him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be beleeued vpon, &amp; our ſelues of our ſelues to be beloued
<pb facs="tcp:25051:37"/>in him one of another.</p>
            <p>There is neuer a threede in Papiſtrie but is ſtayned. They haue neither perfect <hi>faith</hi> which they deuide betwene God &amp; his creatures, nor true <hi>loue</hi> (which wanteth the bonde of loue, true <hi>faith</hi>) nor due repentance haue they. For al their repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in whiſpering in a Prieſtes eare, or abſteyning from the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate vſe of certaine meates, in which they put a ſatiſfaction: as if God were pleaſed &amp; ſinne done away with the eating of fiſh and not of fleſhe, or the not vſage of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his creatures reuerently w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thankes giuing.<note place="margin">1. Tim, 4.3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But in deed the <hi>ſowre herbes</hi> wherwith we muſt eate his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeouer, are a penitent hearte, a broken and contrite ſpirite, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe fooliſh fleſh laboureth and werieth it ſelfe in ſinfull wayes, and doeth eftſoones offende in
<pb facs="tcp:25051:38"/>thought, worde, &amp; deede, againſt his diuine maieſtie. And this if we do, crauing pardon for al our ſinnes and miſdoings, no doubt hee will conſider our ſighes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue our prayers, forgiue our ſinnes, accept vs for iuſt, accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vs for his own, &amp; make vs meete partakers of his heauenly table.</p>
            <p>Being thus prepared, inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in fayth,<note place="margin">Meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> enflamed in loue, &amp; after a ſort repaired by repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> maiſt preſent thy ſelf before the Lord. Wherin (as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wiſema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in an other caſe) <hi>meditate</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine and againe what is ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee,<note place="margin">Pro. 23.1.</note> leaſt thy table bee thy ſnare, thy meate thy bane, thine own knife cut thine own throte. Bread which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtaffe of ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth to man, wil choke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hawke. The faithfull, charitable and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant ſoule partaketh ſaluation, the vnworthie receiuer eateth &amp; drinketh his owne damnation:
<pb facs="tcp:25051:38"/>euen as the Babylonian dragon brake aſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der as ſoone as he recei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> balles y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Daniel put into his mouth, as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtory reporteth.</p>
            <p>Wherfore y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> godly man &amp; child of God, ponder with thy ſelfe, enter into thy conſcience, let co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient thoughtes &amp; meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons occupy &amp; poſſeſſe thy inward partes. And that thou mayeſt ſo do, reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber what y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art a doing, what worke thou haſt in hande. Doe this in remembrance of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Plutar. in vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Numae, Hoe Age.</note> feede on him in thy ſoule with thanks, &amp; ſet forth (liuely) his death w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> praiſe. Pharaohs butler forgate Ioſeph,<note place="margin">Gen. 40.23</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnclean hog neuer loketh vp to him that beateth downe the maſte from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tree. Lift vp your heartes, wee lift them vp vnto the Lord. They are the wordes of the church ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, godly wordes. It is meete &amp; right ſo to doe, and our bounden duetie that we ſhould at al times
<pb facs="tcp:25051:39"/>recorde his goodneſſe, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially at the time of this action, to ſhewe foorth his death till his comming againe, &amp; agnize our ſinnes, which being the cauſe of his dying plucked y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of God out from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> boſome of the father to be crucified on earth, of, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, and for ſinfull men.</p>
            <p>The maymes wee receiued in Adam &amp; remaine yet in vs, are three. <hi>Sinne, Ignorance, Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> The remedies whereof we finde in Chriſt, the Phyſition of our ſoules. <hi>Medicus eſt miniſter naturae:</hi> that which is wanting by nature, is ſupplied by grace.</p>
            <p>Chriſt is a Prieſt to cleanſe our ſinnes, a Prophet to inſtruct our rudeneſſe, &amp; a Kinge to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quere our enemies. But his Prieſthoode and his ſacrifice we chiefly celebrate in this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which alſo may be and is termed therfore a Sacrifice, not
<pb facs="tcp:25051:39"/>of Chriſt, but to Chriſt in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrifice of praiſe, the calues of our lippes, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe of thankes giuing: and this Leuites fire ſhould neuer go out, and in the preſent, flame all abroad. Wherein we beleeue in heart, &amp; confeſſe with mouth, that Ieſus Chriſt came into the world to ſaue ſinners, being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite God, was made perfite man. Man, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he might die: God, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in dying, he might ſatiſfie for man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind: for becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the fleſh alone profiteth nothing, his manhood was not ſufficient, except alſo he had bene very God. Wherfore God, euen our God ſo exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loued the world, that he gaue his onely begotten ſonne (and therefore he alſo naturaly God, the ſonne like the father) to bee the ranſome for the ſinnes of the world.<note place="margin">Iſai. 53.5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>The chaſtiſement of our peace was vpon him,</hi> the peace
<pb facs="tcp:25051:40"/>ours, the chaſtiſement his, all ſufficient for all the ſinnes both of body and ſoule of all ſinners.</p>
            <p>The grieuouſnes and bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of which cup may be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, in that our Sauiour after a ſort taſted thereof, and it taſted bitter: put forth his hand to take it, pulled it in againe, &amp; began to tremble: his very ſoule was ſorowful, praied earneſtly, went out and prayed againe, that if it were poſſible, it might paſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, needed an Angell for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, ſwet water &amp; drops of blood.</p>
            <p>If there were nothing herein but an vſuall death, woulde Chriſt thus haue bene afflicted? The heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue ſuffred more, &amp; with more pacience apparant: therfore there muſt be, and was more in it, and yet he is not come to the bitternes in the bottom of the cup. Thoſe former agonies were but hony in compariſon of
<pb facs="tcp:25051:40"/>the conflict with Sathan which followed, and the wrath of his father which enſued, when all ſinnes, as heauy as hell, &amp; more then the ſtarres of heauen, or the ſand of the ſea were layed in one vpon him, and he for them made a curſe and execration,<note place="margin">Iſa. 53.8.</note> the iuſt executed for the vniuſt, one for all.</p>
            <p>A childe is borne to vs, and giuen vnto vs, and liued for vs. This might comfort Ieruſalem at the heart: but the end &amp; perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our ioy, and his ſorowe, was his death on croſſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in conſiſteth the thankfull me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation I ſpeake of, holpen by breaking of the bread, and the powring foorth of the wine before our ſight: wherein the default of our aduerſaries ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth greatly, that debarreth the people of ſo great an helpe. For be it that perfect Chriſt be
<pb facs="tcp:25051:41"/>communicated in the bread, yet in the wine ſignifica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly is reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled his bloodſheding moſt. And howe dare they alter the Lordes inſtitution? As he tooke bread, <hi>euen ſo</hi> he tooke the cup:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> then if bread be requiſite, ſo is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cup al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. For as he tooke the one, ſo he tooke the other.<note place="margin">Eckius in ench.</note> Eckius woulde proue his halfe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion out of his <hi>Paternoſter: giue vs this day our daily bread.</hi> A begger is neuer out of his way. What ſcripture wil not ſerue for any purpoſe, if y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do for his? Saint Paul teacheth what the Lorde did, and what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Corinthians ſhould do <hi>till Chriſt his comming</hi> in the cloudes, hee meaneth what al poſteritie was to do. For thoſe Corinthians are gone the way of all fleſhe, &amp; their church raſed. He telleth them, &amp; in them vs: <hi>Other thinges at his comming he would diſpoſe of</hi> (as of indifferent circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtances.) But
<pb facs="tcp:25051:41"/>for the lawfull and inuiolable v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the Sacrament in both kindes, <hi>he deliuered as he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dauid ſlewe the Gyant with one ſtone, but he toke more then one out of the brook. Chriſt is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in his word, by his ſpirit, in baptiſme, ſacramentaly in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or rather in both the ſignes of the Supper ioyntly taken as he ordeyned. So ſufficiently and aboundantly hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for his houſhold, bread made of many graynes, and alſo wine of many grapes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> anſwerably we being many, may bee one in him and hee in vs, expecting the accompliſhment of our ioy to the full, no more in ſignes &amp; figures in earth, but apparantly to eate and drincke at Chriſtes table w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him in the kingdome of heauen, where <hi>we ſhal ſit on ſeates &amp; iudge the twelue tribes of Iſrael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke. 22.30</note> 
               <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25051:42"/>
There are certaine kindes both of byrdes and beaſtes,<note place="margin">Conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> whoſe meate wil not tarie w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them, but paſſeth quickly away <hi>recto inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtino</hi> Such beaſtes neuer chew the cud. And ſome men not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like or worſe then beaſtes, medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate litle of whom they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten and fed, what they feede on or in what ſorte, much leſſe doth the meat digeſt with them to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g men in Chriſt, as if Sara were their mother, &amp; Agar their nurſe, or as if they were nurſed with milke &amp; wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with poyſon, and the meate naught and woulde not proue with them, ſo doe they liue. In comming to the Seruice &amp; Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes, eyther for company or cuſtome ſake, they looke one way with the godly, but in their conuerſation, they row another way, and ſhewe in their deedes, of what felowſhip they are. They
<pb facs="tcp:25051:42"/>paſſe through the redde ſea, but murmure in the wildernes, nay euen at the redde ſea offend they God. In pretence ſomwhat they are, but inwardly nothing, and in fact naught. Their windows be not ſcued as Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s were, to giue a full light into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe to their owne heartes, in hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie ſomewhat is ſhewed, the window wide enough outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>Fayth, Loue, Repentance,</hi> to ſight are ſet forth, in performa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce euery one is for him ſelfe, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thankefull to God, neyther charitable to his neighbor, and both without remorſe. Theſe thinges ought not to be ſo, this Paſſeouer would not be ſo eaten, our loynes ſo ſoone vngirded, &amp; our ſtaues throwen away, the water of Baptiſme trampled on, the bread and wine, or the body and blood of Chriſt thus receiued all in vaine. Were it that the
<pb facs="tcp:25051:43"/>naughtye liuer could bee a good beleeuer for the time, or were it, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as water he might be whote im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately before and at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> action of receiuing, yet if when the fire is remoued, the cold qualities re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne againe, what auayleth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> former heate? A cole is red while it is in the fire: when the fire is out, his blacke and naturall co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour returneth by &amp; by againe, and then light it againe, and it ſeemeth red againe, but yet in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende it conſumeth to aſhes. The bone that is often ſet in ioynte,<note place="margin">Auguſt de tem. Ser. 58.</note> will hardly be wel ioyned often. Let no man preſume of ſinning, nor yet deſpaire of mercie. The Sacraments, as they are ſeales of mercy, ſo are they alſo bondes of obedience: &amp; as God will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme on his part al, ſo muſt we endeuour to ſhew our ſelus due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful in al good works. Wherun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to to perſwade, if there were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="tcp:25051:43"/>els but this, this may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: that becauſe Chriſt our Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeouer is offered vp,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.</note> we keepe an holy feaſt vnto the Lorde, not in the leauen of wickednes, but in the ſweete bread of a ſyncere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and vpright conuerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Chriſt Ieſu.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>
               <hi>A prayer vpon conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> generally of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Almightie God &amp; moſt merciful Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who of thy te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der kindneſſe, haſt choſen thine elect to euerlaſting ſaluation before al times, and in due time haſt called them to the knowledge of thy good will, reueiled in thy word, &amp; ſealed with the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb facs="tcp:25051:44"/>of thine own ordaining, we thy humble ſeruants, and by mercie in Chriſt thine adopted ſonnes, pray thy fatherly good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to make vs meete partakers of theſe &amp; al other thy benefits ſo largely euer more beſtowed and powred vpon vs.</p>
            <p>Let vs not (O Lorde) neither detaine y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trueth of thy word in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnrighteouſnes of a ſinfull life: neither ſuffer vs (deare Father) to receiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pledges of thy endles loue in vaine, but to the endes that thou haſt appointed them.</p>
            <p>Wherefore graunt vs thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly grace, that we thy choſen people may vſe thy holy ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to moſt holy purpoſes: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to the further increaſe of our weake faith, to the comfort of our wan hope, to the enflaming of our colde and frozen charitie in theſe hard and euill dayes, to the dutifull and thankefull ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:25051:44"/>foorth of the glory of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly name, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>A prayer to be ſaide with <hi>meditation of our Baptiſme.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Erciful Father, we miſerable and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men feele with in our ſelues, and therefore are forced to breake forth &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in our fleſh dwelleth no good thing.</p>
            <p>O Lorde, thou lookeſt downe from heauen, and beholdeſt the ſonnes of men and their ſinnes, they are infinitely great, and in nomber mo then the heares of our head or the ſtarres of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: they can not be hidden.</p>
            <p>Our children gather ſtickes, our fathers kindle the fire, our mothers kneade dough to make cakes to ſerue other gods. There
<pb facs="tcp:25051:45"/>is not one that doth good, no not one. We are all borne in ſinne, conceiued in iniquity, and the whole race of our life is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally naught. We are not able to dreame of a good thought, and when we haue done all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we can doe, or if we could do al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are commaunded, yet were we vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſeruants, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we appeale from thy iuſtice, (O moſt iuſt God) to thy mercie ſeate, and throne of grace: for we feare nothing more then the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of our droſſy workes.</p>
            <p>O Lord, waſh thou vs that we may be white, for in our ſelues we are altogether blacke, purge vs that we may be cleane, ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie vs that we may be holy, cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe our eares and heartes and other partes, ſeare our pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted lippes with the cole of thy ſpirit, &amp; create a new heart win vs, this olde heart of ours will
<pb facs="tcp:25051:45"/>not ſerue, waſh vs more &amp; more, and we ſhalbe cleane.</p>
            <p>This thou haſt promiſed in thy word (O gracious God) and in the Sacrament of our newe birth is this nowe fully ſet forth and ſealed: wherefore with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence wee appeare before thee in prayer, not truſting in our owne merites, which are not, but in thy manifolde and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe mercies, which as a great and pure ſtreame of water ſhall make vs whiter then the ſnow, and clearer then the Chriſtall glaſſe.</p>
            <p>O Lorde haue mercie vpon vs according to thy great mercy, put away our iniquities, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don our offences, cancell the bill of debt, quench y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flames of luſt, plucke out the ſting of ſinne, mortifie our fleſh more &amp; more, kill and burie the olde man, bruiſe the ſerpents head, drown
<pb facs="tcp:25051:46"/>the ſpirituall Pharao, and all Egypt, that we in a good time may bee preſented perfectly blameleſſe in thy ſight, through Chriſt our Lord, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>
               <hi>A prayer to be ſaid imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly</hi> before the receiuing the holy Communion.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Almightie GOD, who in thy eternal wiſedom haſt built thee an houſe, and he wen out the pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars thereof: choſen a Church which ſhall not faile, killed thy vittayles, mixed thy wine, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared a Table, &amp; haſt ſent foorth thy miniſters to cry in the open ſtreetes, and to inuite vnto this feaſt in thy worde and Goſpell: and yet haſt denounced that the ſcornefull, the wicked and the wilfull ſinner ſhall haue no part
<pb facs="tcp:25051:46"/>nor portion with thee, grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vs grace (O Lord) that we may ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually heare, and willingly followe the voyce of thy calling, and that the ſeede of thy worde, being ſhed in to our eares, may take deepe roote in our heartes, and bring forth fruit according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in a godly conuerſation.</p>
            <p>And whereas not only by thy worde, but by thy Sacraments alſo we are fed at thy hande, and ſpecially in the Supper of thy Sonne our Lorde his inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we craue the aſſiſtance of thy holy ſpirite, worthily to prepare vs for the receiuing of ſo heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a banquet.</p>
            <p>Otherwiſe, who or what are we to entertaine, or to be enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in this manner? we are vnworthy the leaſt of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, much leſſe are we worthie that the heire of all ſhould enter vnder the roofe of our ſoule, or
<pb facs="tcp:25051:47"/>that our vncleane feete ſhoulde once ſtep within thy courts, and yet thou haſt commaunded we ſhoulde repaire to thy Temple, and receiue at thy table.</p>
            <p>Wherefore (good Lorde) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare thou vs aright that wee may bee prepared, dwell in vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may dwell in thee, knocke at the gates of our heartes that we may ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto thee, ſup with vs, that we may ſup with thee, encreaſe our faith and loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thee, and in thee towarde our neighbours. And albeit we offend often, &amp; fall many times, yet ſtay thou vs by thy mercifull hand that we neuer fall away. Finally, ſtrengthen our weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes with thy euerlaſting foode, neyther looke vpon our imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, but on the perfectneſſe of thy ſonnes oblation, in whoſe name we pray, that thou endue vs euer with an humble and a
<pb facs="tcp:25051:47"/>contrite ſpirite for all our ſinnes paſt, &amp; with a conſtant purpoſe alwaies hereafter vnfainedly to ſerue and pleaſe thee in newnes of life to our liues ende, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>A thankes giuing vpon the receiuing of the holy Communion.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y ſoule praiſe thou the Lorde, and all the powers with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me praiſe his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly name.</p>
            <p>My heauie ſoule awake, praiſe the Lorde, forget not his benefites, ſhewe not thy ſelfe an vnthankefull thiſtle being wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered with ſo many graces.</p>
            <p>He faſhioned the rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d world, &amp; all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is therein, yea with a more ſpeciall care he guideth the feete
<pb facs="tcp:25051:48"/>of his Saintes.</p>
            <p>He clotheth the lilies of the fielde, and feedeth the birdes of the ayre, but he apparelleth his choſen with the cloth of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe in the familie of his Sonne, and feedeth them with the bread of life.</p>
            <p>In him we are, and are rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate, by him wee liue and are fed at his owne table, in him, &amp; by his ſpirit we moue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al godly motions, and this comforte no man can take from vs.</p>
            <p>Al good giftes deſcend from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, and the prayſe of all is due to thee (O Lord) euen as the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters iſhue from the ſea, and to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſea returne againe.</p>
            <p>O then what ſhall we render vnto our louing God, for all his kindnes? he hath not ſpared his onely begotten ſonne to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death the death of the Croſſe, for our ſakes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25051:48"/>
Thou O Lord art not pleaſed with mans inuentions: onely thou haſt willed that wee bee a thankfull people, and that wee continue a freſhe and gratefull remembrance of thy goodnes for euer.</p>
            <p>The calues of our lippes, the incenſe of prayer and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrifice of prayſe thou wilt accept.</p>
            <p>Wherefore (O my ſoule) praiſe the Lord, ſet forth thy Sauiours death, reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber his paſſion, ſhew not thy ſelfe vnkinde, feede on him in thy heart, and be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, in a full aſſurance of all his mercies in Ieſus Chriſt. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at London by Chriſtopher Barker, Printer to the Queenes moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Maieſtie.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25051:49"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25051:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25051:51"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25051:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:25051:52"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:25051:52"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:25051:53"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:25051:53"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:25051:54"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:25051:54"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:25051:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:25051:55"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:25051:56"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:25051:56"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
